http://youtu.be/kYxKjMAFDBE
http://youtu.be/kYxKjMAFDBE
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: So now that we understand numbers systems, one of the
DR. RAMESH YERRABALLI: bây giờ ta đã biết các hệ đếm,
questions that often comes is how do computers represent numbers?
1 câu hỏi là làm sao máy tính thể hiện những con số?
That is, do numbers have to always be of a certain length?
Có phải là những số đều phải có chiều dài như nhau?
And if they are of a certain length, what do they represent?
Nếu có cùng chiều dài, nó đại diện cho cái gì?
The most common number we represent on computers are integers.
Số phổ biến nhất mà ta thể hiện trên máy tính là số integer.
Integers are the most common numbers, and integers, by definition, are on
Số integer là những số
the number line you have positive integers.
nguyên dương.
So some maximum positive integer, zero to maximum, and some negative on the
Số nguyên dương từ 0 tới vô cùng, và
negative number line.
số nguyên âm.
So we have numbers represented on the number line.
Ta có những số trên trục số.
So for the most part, we are happy to represent numbers as being unsigned.
Đa số trường hợp, số không dấu là đủ.
And that's what we did in the last description.
Đó là cái tôi đã làm.
When we say a number this unsigned we primarily focusing on numbers that
Khi nói số không dấu, ta hiểu là số
range from zero to some positive maximum.
nguyên dương.
So unsigned numbers don't have a positive or negative sign.
Số không dấu không có dấu cộng hay trừ.
So unsigned numbers.
Cho nên nó là số không dấu.
So let's take an example of an unsigned number.
Ví dụ cho 1 số không dấu.
Here is an unsigned number, 10001101.
10001101.
And if I told you that this is an unsigned number which is in binary, we
Nếu tôi cho bạn biết đây là số binary không dấu,
know what it represents.
ta sẽ biết nó nghĩa là gì.
We know that it represents, again just to make the point I say that this as a
Ta sẽ biết nó nghĩa là gì
position of 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and 7.
đây là vị trí 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and 7.
And so one of the convenient things to do is to look at the numbers and just
Để cho tiện ta nhìn vào những số này
identify the coefficients that are non-zero.
lựa những hệ số khác 0.
In this case, the one coefficients.
Trong trường hợp này là những số 1.
So the coefficients occur in positions 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and 7.
Những hệ số này có ở vị trí 0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, and 7.
And the place values, accordingly, are 1, that's 2, this is 4, because that's
Tương ứng với những vị trí này là 1, là 2, đây là 4, bởi vì
2 to the 2, this is 8, and this is 16, 32, 64, and 128.
2 mũ 2, đây là 8, và đây là 16, 32, 64 và 128.
So I'm going to write this number as 1 plus 4 plus 8 plus 128, which is the
Vậy số này là 1 cộng 4 cộng 8 cộng 128
number 141 in base 10.
là 141 cơ số 10.
So what if we want to represent numbers that can have a sign?
Vậy số có dấu thì biểu diễn thế nào?
That can be a positive number or a negative number?
Nó là số dương hay số âm?
So let's take a look at what such a representation would look like.
Thử xem nó có thể biểu diễn thế nào.
So the number, 01000110, let's say this were a signed number in base 2.
Số 01000110, giả dụ nó là số có dấu cơ số 2.
What we do when we're representing signed numbers is we assign a special
Để biểu diễn số có dấu, ta gán
meaning to the most significant bit we call this the sign bit.
1 ý nghĩa đặc biệt cho bit cao nhất, gọi là bit dấu.
And the significance is that a sign bit is either a zero or a one to
Biết dấu là 0 hay 1
represent positive numbers or negative numbers.
đại diện cho số dương hoặc âm.
So here's a number because it has a zero here it has to
Với số này, bit dấu là 0, nên nó là
be a positive number.
số dương.
So let's understand what this number represents.
Hãy xem giá trị của nó.
So this number then, has the bit.
Số này có 1 bit.
This bit represents a place value of 2.
Bit ở vị trí có giá trị là 2.
This represents a place value of 4.
Chỗ này là 4.
And then we have 6, 8, 16, 32, and 64.
này ta có 6, 8, 16, 32, và 64.
So this number then, represents 64 plus 4 plus 2.
Vậy số này là 64 cộng 4 cộng 2.
Which is 70 in base 10.
là 70 cơ số 10.
Now, this is a number that is a positive number.
Đây là số dương.
So what if we have a signed number that is a negative number?
Số âm thì sao?
A signed number that is negative, let's take a simple
1 số có dấu là số âm, ví dụ
example of such a number.
1 số đơn giản.
Here is a signed number that is negative.
Đây là 1 số âm
So 10001101.
10001101.
And again, we notice that because this bit is a 1, this tells us that this
Nhắc lại, để ý bit dấu là 1,
number has to be a negative number.
đó là dấu hiệu nhận biết số âm.
So what does it represent?
Giá trị nó là gì?
Well, our place values are 1, that's a 2, that's 4, that's an 8, and this
Giá trị vị trí là 1, là 2, đây là 4, là 8,
still has a place value which is 128, but now we notice that this number
có 1 chỗ có giá trị 128, nhưng ta để ý là
will actually represent 1 plus 4 plus 8 plus a -128.
giá trị thực sự là 1 cộng 4 cộng 8 cộng -128.
Because that's a negative number.
Bởi vì đây là số âm.
So this number represents a -115 in base ten.
nên số này là -115 trong hệ 10.
So in summary then, let's see if we can understand something about the
Tóm lại, ta nên nhớ khoảng mà
ranges that these two number representations can capture.
2 cách biểu diễn này có thể bao phủ.
So let's look at how signed and unsigned numbers go from, for example,
Xem số không dấu và có dấu bắt đầu từ đâu, ví dụ,
if I have eight bits that I have eight bits to represent, then I can go from
Nếu tôi có 8 bit, tôi có thể bắt đầu từ
zero, so from here, all the way up to 255.
0, cho tới 255.
Now if I have a signed numbers, again in eight bits, because I have to
Nếu là số có dấu, với 8 bit, bởi vì tôi phải biểu diễn
represent both positive and negative numbers, I will only be able to
cả số dương và số âm, tôi chỉ có thể
represent 127 on the positive side, and I will represent -128 on the
đếm tới số 127 ở chiều dương, và số -128
negative side.
ở chiều âm.
So the range is from -128 to +127.
Nên khoảng bao phủ của nó là -128 tới +127.
Here is a neat little trick that we use sometimes when we want to show
Đây là 1 mánh để biểu diễn 1 số
numbers and show them in, not in their full glory in binary, but to
không phải bằng binary,
show them as in hex.
mà bằng hex.
So we could write this number again as a 8 followed by a D, because that's a
Ta có thể ghi lại số này là 8 và D, bởi vì
1101, which is 12 plus 1, which is 13, 13 stands for D. So I could represent
1101, là 12 cộng 1, là 13, 13 là D, nên tôi viết số này là
this number as 0x8D.
0x8D.
And that's simply a convenient way so that when we look at numbers, it's
Đây chỉ là cách tiện lợi hơn, nên đôi khi
sometimes simpler to represent them as binary.
sẽ đơn giản hơn khi viết số binary.
Represent them as hex, or represent them as decimal.
Đôi khi là số hex, đôi khi là số thập phân.
OK.
Tất cả đều được.